你得发誓
I need your oath.
新矿石的第一丝踪迹
The first traces of a new ore.
埃尔隆德保证 吉尔加拉德派他来这里并没有恶意
Elrond has been very convincing in his assurances
埃尔隆德的话让人非常信服
that Gil-galad bore no ill intent when he sent him here.
感觉事有蹊跷
There is something more at work.
去林顿吧
Go to Lindon.
看看是怎么回事
Find out what.
你被踢出海上卫队了  你们仨全部淘汰
You're off the Sea Guard! All three of you!
够了
Enough!
我毁了朋友们的生活 羞辱了家门
I just ruined my friends' lives, shamed our family name.
你去找那些在旧瞭望塔避难的人
Go to the Men who have taken refuge in the old watchtower.
给他们捎个口信
Deliver to them a message.
你的人民要想保全性命 必须放弃这些土地的所有权
That your people may live if you forsake all claim to these lands
并向他宣誓效忠
and swear fealty to him.
总有一天 我们真正的国王会归来
One day, our true king will return.
我相信你关在地牢里的那一位
I believe the man you hold in your dungeons
是流亡在外 下落不明的南方大地王位继承人
is the lost heir in exile to the throne of the Southlands.
我请求您与我并肩作战
I call on you to fight with me...
-我愿意出征  -我愿意出征
-I will serve! -I will serve!
避免索隆将他们的土地据为己有
...before Sauron claims their lands for his own.
你撒谎
You have lied,
还把危险的外族人带了进来
brought a dangerous outsider into our midst.
我们要掉队了
We're going to be left behind.
这就是我们大家不会掉队的原因
This is how we keep up with the others.
因为他会帮我们 我们也会帮他
He helps us, and... and we help him.
指环王：力量之戒
第一季第五集
本WEB版外挂字幕由  风吹来的那片云  双语合并
“千禧”
My great thumb. My great thumb.
不对 应该念迁…迁徙
No. Mi... Migration.
迁-徙
Like, mi-gra-tion.
意思就是搬家 我们毛脚族搬家就叫做迁徙
Means, like, to move. What we do, Harfoots.
是这样 我们会去老林子过冬
You see, we... we winter in Old Forest,
仲夏时节 我们会 趁蜗牛鲜美时前往诺菲德山谷捕食
and mid-summer, we make for Norfield Glen to snail while the snailing's good.
-“蜗牛”  -没错 蜗牛
-"Snails, snails"? -Snails, yeah.
在橡树叶刚刚开始变红的秋天 我们前往格罗夫果园
And at the first blush of the oak leaves, we head to the Grove.
整个果园
A whole orchard,
到处都是苹果 李子 杏子 胡萝卜 你肯定很喜欢
popping with bar apples, plums, apricots, carrots, you'll... you'll love it.
当然了 唯一的麻烦是 从一地迁徙到另一地要历经重重危险
Of course, the only trouble is there's a hundred perils between here and there.
“危险”
"Perils"?
就是威胁
Like a danger.
比如人类 狼群 雾 雨
You know, big folk, wolves, fog, rain,
山岭食人妖 洞穴食人妖 只要能杀死你的都算是威胁
hill-trolls, cave-trolls, anything that'll kill ya.
“杀死”
"Kill"?
意思就是把某个东西弄死掉
Means to make somethin' dead.
那我就是个危险
I'm peril.
不 你不是的
No. No, no, you're not.
-更像是说… -不 萤火虫
-It's more... -No. Fireflies.
那是一次意外 就是…
-That was just an accident. It's...
你不是危险
You're not a peril.
你很好
You're good.
我很好
I'm good?
你很好 因为你是来帮忙的
You're good. Because you're here to help.
诺瑞
Nori!
好了 其他人现在应该准备好了
Oh, great. Others should be ready by now.
小腿跑起来
Quick sticks!
我们走 来啊
Let's go. Come on.
我…
I... I'm...
我很好
I'm good.
你再敢用那根拐杖戳我
Poke me with that crutch again,
我就趁你睡觉的时候 拔掉你脚趾上的毛发
I'll pluck the hair off your toes in your sleep.
那你拔毛的时候 顺便把我的耳朵也揪掉吧
And I'll pluck off my ears while you're at it.
省得我再听你的鼾声
It'd save me listenin' to your snorin'.
闭嘴吧 我才不打呼噜呢
Oh, stuff. I do not snore.
-你确实打呼噜 -你确实打呼噜
-Yes, you do.
快走吧 动起来 不迈腿永远都去不了格罗夫
Come on, now. Grove's not gonna migrate to us.
你要是给我们唱你妈妈的赶路歌 没准能帮我们走快点
Might help us move faster if you sang us your mam's walking song.
是啊 唱吧 波比 喊两嗓子
Yeah, go on, Pops, give us a warble.
唱吧 能给我们赶路加油鼓劲
Oh, come on, it'll do us some good.
太阳正在落下
-The sun is fast fallin'
落在森岩的树林后方
Beneath trees of stone
塔中之光
The light in the tower
不再是家乡
No longer my home
过去灯火朦胧
Past eyes of pale fire
黑沙做我的睡床
Black sand for my bed
我用所知的一切
I trade all I've known
换取未知的未来
For the unknown ahead
呼唤我 遥远之地 请呼唤我
Call to me Call to me lands far away
罗瓦尼安之丘-韦德布鲁克
因为我现在 必须在这流浪的日子里游荡
For I must now wander this wandering day
副崖-灰色沼泽
我必须游荡
Away I must wander
在这流浪的日子里
This wandering day
我缺水
Of drink I have little
我少食
And food I have less
我的力量告诉我不行 但是这条路要求我踏足
My strength tells me no But the path demands yes
鲑鳟弯
我双腿很短 而道阻且长
My legs are so short And the way is so long
无法休息 何谈舒适
I've no rest nor comfort
无所慰藉 唯有歌声
No comfort, but song
西斯尔戴尔-辫子
为我歌唱 遥远之地 请为我歌唱
Sing to me, sing to me Lands far away
请起身指引我度过这流浪的日子
Oh, rise up and guide me This wandering day
请答应要找到我
Please promise to find me
在这个流浪的日子
-This wandering day
最终 他们的答案来了
-At last comes their answer
穿过寒冷和霜冻
Through cold and through frost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder or wander are lost
不论悲伤
No matter the sorrow
不计成本
No matter the cost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder Or wander are... Lost
隧道挖通了 大人
The tunnel is complete, my lord.
给我看看你的手臂
Your arm. Show it to me.
感觉怎么样
How does it feel?
像被火烤一样疼 父亲大人
Like fire, Lord-father.
我真希望你能像我一样感受阳光
I wish you could feel it like I do.
因为太阳很快就要消失了
For soon, it will be gone.
我身体里能感受到温暖的那部分 也将随之消失
And with it, the part of me that knew its warmth as well.
我会想念它的
I shall miss it.
是时候了 去召集军团吧
Summon the legions. It is time.
我们的敌人扬言要发起进攻
-Our enemy vows to attack.
要想活命
In exchange for mercy,
敌人命令我们放弃这座瞭望塔
we've been ordered to abandon this tower
并向他们的指挥官宣誓效忠
and swear fealty to their commander.
我明白我不是 你们翘首以盼的那个国王
I know I'm not the king you have awaited.
但如果你们选择和我并肩战斗
But if you choose to stand with me and fight,
那这座瞭望塔 将不再会是我们脆弱的招牌
this tower will no longer be a reminder of our frailty,
而将会变成我们力量的象征
but a symbol of our strength.
有谁愿意和我并肩作战
Who will stand with me?
你们当中有谁愿意奋起作战
Who among you will stand and fight?
-好的 我们战斗吧 -好的
-Aye, let's do it. -Aye.
奋起作战
Stand and fight?
你们会死的
You will die.
要我说 我们最好碰碰运气
I say it'd be better to take our chances
臣服于所谓的敌人
bowing to the supposed enemy.
我直视过敌人的眼睛
I have looked that enemy in the eye.
他拯救不了你
He's not your deliverance.
那你觉得你能
You think you are?
指望精灵
Elf?
我要替祖先说句话
I'll say this for our ancestors.
敌人并没有杀他们啊
They lived!
只要团结一致 我们就能活下来
Together, we can survive this.
如果跟我走 我们必定会活下来
Follow me, and together, we will!
来吧 都跟我走 来吧
Come on. Let's go. Come on. Follow me. Come on!
来吧
-Come on!
跟我走
Follow me!
希奥
Theo!
这是我们的好机会 好时机 快来
It's our chance. It's our time. Come on.
跟我一起走 来吧 小伙子 跟我来
With me. Come on, lad. Follow me, lad.
能帮我一把吗
Right. Okay. Give me a hand, will ya?
再高点…
Higher. Higher!
小伙子们 这一轮足够了
-Enough for that run, lads.
现在往外运吧
Ferry it out now.
-父亲 -伊熙尔杜
-Father. -Isildur.
我们能聊聊吗
May we speak?
为什么没有选我进远征军
Why wasn't I chosen for the expedition?
-我以为你要去西部 -不去了
-Thought you were going west. -Not anymore.
我要先做点 配得上努门诺尔人做的事
Not till I've done something worthy of Númenor.
那是什么事呢 用你自己的话来说
And what is that? In your words.
我描述不出来
I don't have words for it.
所以我才非常努力地寻找
That's why I'm trying so hard to find it.
所以我才来寻求您的帮助
Why I'm asking for your help.
我倒是希望能帮你
Wish I could provide it.
但志愿者的数量 远远超出了我们能容纳的范围
But we've far more volunteers than we could ever hope to accommodate.
这城市有一半的人想要登上那些船
Half the city wants a spot on those boats.
把我塞进队列的前排
Slip me to the front of the line.
你有什么资格
What are your qualifications?
-“资格”  -你隶属于海上卫队吗
-"Qualifications"? -Do you belong to the Sea Guard?
-你明知道我比水手厉害得多… -你隶属于海上卫队吗
-You know I'm twice the sailor... -Do you belong to the Sea Guard?
女王卫队呢 商人公会呢
What about the Queen's Guard? Merchant's Guild?
-看来有正式编制才是重点 -骑士公会呢
-This is about uniform. -Horseman's Guild?
你太扯了
You're being absurd.
你还在假装 忠于这座岛上的传统的时候
While you were feigning fidelity to the traditions of this isle,
这些人已经在将传统发扬光大了
these men were living them.
他们想尽办法贡献力量 志愿出征
Finding ways to contribute. To serve.
这些东西显然你并不在乎
Something of which you evidently care little.
我在乎 而且我准备好出征了
I care. I'm ready to serve.
只有这件事能让我感到自豪
Nothing would make me prouder.
但是你错失了良机
But you had your chance.
而且你已经做出了选择
And you made your choice.
让努门诺尔人冒着生命之险
-Risk Númenorean lives
就为了一些肮脏的中洲南方人 和一个好战的精灵
for some grimy Southlander and a warmongering Elf?
法拉宗国师  你为什么要让我们的亲人去送死
Consul Pharaz?n! Why are you sending our kinsmen off to die?
法拉宗
-Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n!
-法拉宗  -跟我来
-Pharaz?n! -Come with me.
请原谅我没发消息 这周太难熬了
Forgive me for not sending word to you sooner. Been a trying week.
他为什么不阻止这一切
Why didn't he stop this?
-他忠于女王 不论对… -肯定是错
-He's loyal to her. Rightly or... -Wrongly.
很多人和你感觉一样 但这还不足以改变他的想法 但是…
There are many who feel as you do. Not enough to sway him yet, but
只有你可以去说服他 他会听你的
given the right push... Then it must be you. He will listen to you.
我一开口说话 他就闭耳塞听
When I speak, his ears close up.
那你就大点声说
So speak louder.
中洲南方人
Oi, Southlander.
有人找你
You have visitors.
敌人接下来去哪里了
And where did the enemy head next?
我认为敌人继续往南 朝着欧斯提力斯瞭望塔进军
Further south, I should think. Towards the watchtower of Ostirith.
我去通知海上卫队
I'll inform the Sea Guard.
非常感谢 哈尔布兰德大人
My thanks, Lord Halbrand.
我敢肯定 等我们登陆后 你的民众一定会发挥重要作用
I'm certain your fellowship will prove just as invaluable once we make landfall.
登陆
"Landfall?"
加拉德瑞尔告知我们 你希望团结你的人民
Galadriel informed us of your aspiration to unite your people.
她居然这样说
Did she now?
我相信她绝非未加思考脱口而出
I trust she was not speaking in haste?
其实 我的本意是…
As a matter of fact, it was my intention...
我的同伴只是觉得肩上的任务很重
My companion is merely feeling the weight of his task.
但我毫不怀疑 到时候 他会尽自己的一份力量
I have no doubt, come time, he will do his part.
我已经为本次任务背书 希望他能如你所说
Given that I've staked my name upon it, I should hope so.
摄政女王 您父亲请您去一趟塔里
Queen Regent, your father has requested your presence in the tower.
“加拉德瑞尔告知我们”
"Galadriel informed us."
怪不得当时 女王居然知道要去她父亲床边堵截我
I wondered how the queen knew to waylay me at her father's bedside.
没曾想到你为了公会徽章背叛了我
It never occurred to me you'd hand me over for a guild crest.
我之前恳求你放过我 但你却利用了我
You used me. After I all but begged you to let me be.
我刚刚说服努门诺尔派出五艘船
I have just convinced Númenor to send five ships
和五百人来帮助你的人民
and 500 men to aid your people
帮你加冕为王
and place a crown upon your head.
很多人可能会认为是你利用了我
Many might assume you used me.
麻烦另找别人去加冕吧
Find another head to crown.
我不喜欢这里
I don't like it here.
没事的 迪莉 只是树而已
Oh, it's okay, Dil. It's just the trees.
他们选这条路是失心疯了吗
What madness made them go this way?
石头足路就应该被封起来
Rockfoot Pass must be blocked in.
天黑路难行 继续前进
Won't get any easier in the dark. Keep movin'.
“天黑路难行”
"Easier in the dark."
是狼群
Wolves.
你为什么不告诉我到底发生了什么
Why don't you tell me what's really goin' on?
每年的这个时节 这些树林从没有这样光秃秃过
These woods have never been this bare this time of year.
原因太显而易见了
It's as plain as lip fungus.
都怪他 不是吗 那个大家伙
He is responsible, isn't he? The big fella.
你希望我怎么做
What precisely do you expect me to do about it?
做你当初在营地就该做的事
What you ought to have done at the camp.
卸掉他们的推车轮子 丢下他们
-Take their wheels and leave them!
到底要怎么样你才肯做
What's it gonna take?
非得有人变成寡妇
Make a widow of somebody?
或者孤儿吗
Or an orphan?
大家都饿了
People are gettin' hungry.
跟紧了
Stay close.
这很奇怪…
Oh, this is very strange. Most peculiar.
非常奇怪…
Most peculiar.
-你们差点吓死我了 -玛尔娃
-You nearly caused my heart to burst. -Malva.
-我们看到脚印了 -在泥里
-We saw footprints. -In the mud.
请你们一个一个说
-Lots of 'em! -One at a time, please!
快跑
-Run!
快点 快跑
-Come on! Run!
诺瑞
Nori!
Nori! Nori!
诺瑞 快躲开
Nori, get away from there!
诺瑞
-Nori! Nori!
不要 它会咬到你的
No! It'll get you!
坚守阵地 安塔摩
Hold your ground, Ontamo.
让你的父亲感到骄傲
Make your father proud.
他们的击打动作 像北荒原的岩石巨人一样笨拙
Their strokes fall like the Stone-giants of the North Moors.
但是
And yet?
他们没有对付这个敌人的经验
They are untested against this foe.
或许精灵愿意提供一些指导
Perhaps the Elf would be willing to offer some instructions?
杀死奥克的方法有很多种
There are many ways to kill an Orc.
但对你们而言 我建议用简洁有力的方法
But for you, I will keep it strong and simple.
猛刺 旋扭 拔出
Stab, twist, gut.
跟我比划一下
Come at me.
看看谁能伤得了我
We will see who can score flesh.
有谁能打赢精灵 我会提拔他为…
Anyone that does, I will promote...
中尉
To lieutenant.
剑法的核心是平衡 而并非力量
Swordsmanship is about balance, rather than strength.
对战要用你的双脚 而不是双臂
Fight with your feet. Not your arms.
那个精灵正在广场上与一名士兵切磋
The Elf is fighting a soldier in the square.
脚不要站定
Don't plant roots.
要不断移动
-Keep moving.
靠蛮力永远无法战胜奥克
Never trust brute force to best an Orc.
以谋略制胜往往是最容易的
It's often easiest to outmaneuver them.
干得好 中尉
Well done, Lieutenant.
我从来都不知道 铁匠的助手能有这般功夫
Never known a smith's aide who could do that.
现在叫停这一切还为时不晚
It's not too late to stop this.
虽然权杖在你堂姐手中 但众人追随的领袖是你
Your cousin may hold the scepter, but it's you the people follow.
-在众人的帮助下 你可以… -可以什么
-With their help you could... -Could what?
施加你的影响力
Assert your influence.
有的时候 年轻人的愚蠢足以把年长者气哭
Sometimes the folly of youth is enough to make an old man weep.
试图阻止战争算愚蠢吗
Is it folly to try and stop a war?
逆流而上是愚蠢的
It's folly to kick against the current.
是这样 潮水可能涨起来淹死人
You see, the tide may rise and drown a man,
也可能落潮把人卷入海里
or fall and sweep him out to sea.
控制潮水的诀窍 是要知道它接下来会朝哪个方向流动
The trick of mastering the current is to know which way it will turn next.
你曾单枪匹马阻止了上一任国王
You all but single-handedly prevented our last king
把我们拖回老路
from dragging us back to the old ways.
别告诉我你现在无法 改变弥瑞尔的想法
Don't tell me you couldn't sway Míriel's mind now.
是什么让你觉得 弥瑞尔和我的想法不一致
And what makes you think Míriel's mind and my own are not as one on this?
因为我父亲宁可死 也不会接受精灵的命令
Because my father would sooner die than take orders from an Elf.
“精灵的命令”
"Orders from an Elf"?
等这一切结束之后 将会是精灵们听从我们的号令
When all this has ended, Elves will take orders from us.
只要我堂姐愿意 她可以为加拉德瑞尔出战
Now, my cousin can go to war for Galadriel if she wishes.
但我是为了努门诺尔而战
I go to war for Númenor.
这怎么会是为努门诺尔而战呢
How could this be for Númenor?
你都白学了吗
Have you learned nothing?
很快 我们将拯救中洲的下等人
Soon, we will save the low men of Middle-earth,
抬高他们的地位 给他们期待已久的国王
lift them up, and give them the king they've long awaited.
这个国王将永远欠我们的债
A king who will be forever in our debt.
看你现在能不能想明白 这会对我们有什么好处
Now, contemplate, if you can, how that might benefit us.
矿石 森林 贸易 贡品…
Ores, forests, trades, tribute...
所以我可不敢 阻止这场战争 给我千金都不换
I wouldn't dare stop that. Not for all the salt in the sea.
你也不应该阻止这场战争
And neither should you.
这座王国
The kingdom!
-这座王国处于危险之中 我必须… -危险已经过去了 父亲
-The kingdom is in danger. I must... -The danger has passed, Father.
我们正在做 您一直认为我们必须做的事情
We are doing now what you always believed we must.
我们正在恢复与精灵的关系
We're restoring our connection with the Elves.
我要去中洲
I'm going to Middle-earth.
弥瑞尔
Míriel?
我在呢 父亲
Yes, Father.
是我
It's me.
别去中洲
Don't go to Middle-earth.
在那里 等待你的将是…
All that awaits you there is...
是什么 父亲 等待我的将是什么
What, Father? What awaits me?
黑暗
Darkness.
你敢信吗
Can you believe it?
大家都在说你刚才做的事
Everyone's talkin' about what you did.
从来没有见过他们 这样满心喜欢一个外族人
Never seen 'em take a shine to an outsider like this before.
我给你带了一些蜂蜡
Brought you some beeswax.
在你那大爪子上涂一点就没那么疼了
Slather some on that paw, should help with the tenderness.
嘿
Hey.
住手 求你了
Stop. Please.
敬我们两个伟大种族之间的长久联盟
To an enduring union between our two great peoples,
卡扎德人和诺多族
Khazad and Noldor.
-敬联盟 -敬联盟
-To the union. -To the union.
在我们开怀畅饮之前
Before our wines ascend,
都林大人 我想赞扬你
Lord Durin, I should like to commend you.
卡扎督姆一向被称为 矮人王国中最安静的一个
Khazad-d?m has been called the quietest of Dwarven kingdoms,
但是最近几个月 据说你们的熔炉在燃烧
but in recent months, your furnaces are said to be burning
火光亮得都快赶上奥力本尊的眼睛了
as bright as the eyes of Aul? himself.
而且你们的矿井钻得越来越深
Your mines delving ever deeper.
这股新的活力您认为出自哪里呢
To what do you credit this new invigoration?
同样的话我也想问林顿
I might ask the same of Lindon.
用船送走精灵战士 扩建城市
Shipping off its warriors, expandin' its cities.
对精灵来说有点突然 不是吗
Bit sudden for Elves, no?
你们每做一个决定 通常都要花他个好几年…
Typically takes you people weeks just to decide to take a sh...
请允许我…
If I may...
对于我们精灵而言 时间流逝得很慢
The hand of time crawls so slowly for our kind.
我们经常会把 多年的辛苦努力视为短暂的付出
We often overlook the years of effort we perceive as taking but a moment.
希望我们这样不会冒犯到我们的客人
In so doing, I would not wish to offend our guest.
如果能被一个真诚的提问所冒犯
I would think our Dwarven friend far too stout of heart
那这位矮人朋友未免也太顽固了
to be offended by an honest inquiry.
我有个真诚的问题想问你
I have an honest inquiry for you.
你从哪里弄来的这张桌子
From where did you procure the table?
你为什么这么问
Why do you ask?
这种石头只分布在一定的深度
This stone grows only at certain depths.
特别稀少 以至于 我们的共鸣者很少能找到矿床
So rarely do our resonators locate a deposit.
我们将每一块这种石头 都视为珍贵的礼物
We consider each to be a precious gift.
把它留着用于最神圣的目的
We reserve its use for the most sacred purposes.
用来建造纪念碑或坟墓
Monuments or tombs,
纪念我们尊敬的逝者
to our honored dead.
请原谅我们的亵渎 都林大人
Please forgive our sacrilege, Lord Durin.
我们一定会让你 把它带回家 好让它得到应有的尊重
We shall have to send it home with you, so it can be treated with proper respect.
很高兴知道 精灵当中还是存在些许荣誉感的
It's good to know there's still some honor left among the Elves.
陛下
Your Grace.
那么 敬我们两族人民的联盟
To the union of our two peoples, then.
敬联盟
To the union.
你对这个矮人的忠诚令人钦佩
Your loyalty to the Dwarf is admirable.
理应这样忠诚待友
Loyalty to a friend ought to be expected.
不论种族
Regardless of his race.
就凭这个 你就可以向国王撒谎吗
Does it justify lying to your king?
至高王 我想知道 一直在对我撒谎的是不是您
I wonder, High King, if it is in fact you who has been lying to me.
我带着友谊的提议 去了卡扎督姆 但事实上
I went to Khazad-d?m with a proposal of friendship, but in truth,
你却在寻求 更看得见摸得着的东西 不是吗
you sought something far more tangible, didn't you?
你熟悉 《希斯艾格利尔山根之歌》吗
Are you familiar with The Song of the Roots of Hithaeglir?
请复述给我听
-Recount it for me, please.
这是个鲜为人知的传说 大多数人认为它是杜撰的
An obscure legend regarded by most to be a apocryphal.
复述一遍 埃尔隆德佩瑞蒂尔（“半精灵”）
Recount it, Elrond Peredhel.
这首歌讲述了一场战斗
It speaks of a battle,
在迷雾山脉高耸的山峰之间
high among the peaks of the Misty Mountains.
战斗并非因荣耀 或使命而起 而是因为一棵树
Not over honor or duty. But over a tree.
有些人称这棵树里 藏着最后一颗丢失的精灵宝钻
Within which some claim was hidden the last of the lost Silmarils.
战斗的一方是一位精灵战士
On one side, fought an Elven warrior,
心如曼威般纯洁
with a heart as pure as Manw?,
为了保护这棵树 他将所有的光都倾注其中
who poured all of his light into the tree to protect it.
战斗的另一方是魔苟斯的一个炎魔
-On the other, a Balrog of Morgoth,
把他所有的仇恨 都传导到这棵树上 以求将其摧毁
who channeled all his hatred into the tree to destroy it.
在他们无休止的决斗中 闪电击中了这棵树…
Amidst their duel unending, lightning ensnared the tree...
使他们的对抗造就了一股力量…
Forging of their conflict, a power...
这股力量如善良一般纯净而轻盈
A power as pure and light as good.
又像邪恶一样坚强不屈
As strong and unyielding as evil.
他们说这股力量从树根渗入大山深处
They say it seeped down the roots into the mountain depths,
几个世纪以来 它一直在等待
where for centuries now, it has waited.
都林说对了
Durin was right.
那你就是承认矮人确实找到了它
Then you admit the Dwarves did find it.
那种矿石蕴含着丢失的精灵宝钻之光
The ore containing the light of the lost Silmaril.
我只承认这一点
I admit only this.
我答应过都林永远不会 泄露他子民的秘密
I promised Durin never to reveal his people's secrets.
如果说 信守对他子民的承诺
And what if keeping your promise to his people
意味着你的同胞就要厄运难逃呢
meant ensuring the doom of your own?
我们第一次注意到这种情况 刚好在加拉德瑞尔回来之前
We first took notice of it just prior to Galadriel's return.
当时我们希望通过把她送走
We hoped that by sending her away,
抹去战争最后的痕迹
and so bringing an end to the last vestiges of war,
从而就此阻止树的枯萎
we might arrest the decay.
但尽管我们竭尽全力
But despite our every effort,
枯萎还是加速了
our decline has only quickened.
这棵树表面上的枯萎反映了它
The blight upon this tree is but an outer manifestation
内在的实质
of an inner reality.
灵族之光
That the light of the Eldar,
也就是我们的光 正在消逝
our light, is fading.
还有谁知道这件事
Who else knows about this?
只有极少数
Precious few.
我再问最后一次
I ask again, and for the last time,
矮人是不是找到了那种矿石
did the Dwarves find the ore or not?
我向都林发过誓
I swore an oath to Durin.
对有些人来说 如今发誓可能并没有多大意义了
To some, that may now hold little weight.
但在我看来
But in my esteem,
正是誓言才让 我们的灵魂紧紧连接在一起
it is by such things our very souls are bound.
我不打算仅仅为了希望而违背誓言
I do not intend to let mine slip away on the basis of mere hope.
希望从来都不是微不足道的 埃尔隆德…
Hope is never mere, Elrond...
即便希望很渺茫
even when it is meager.
当所有其他感官都睡着了
When all other senses sleep,
希望之眼会率先醒来 最后一个闭上
the eye of hope is first to awaken, last to shut.
如果精灵现在放弃中洲
If the Elves abandon Middle-earth now,
黑暗大军将会在中洲大地上横行
the armies of darkness will march over the face of the earth.
那将会是末日
It will be the end,
不仅是我们精灵族的末日 还是所有种族的末日
not just of our people, but all peoples.
如果能防止这种情况发生的希望
If the hope of preventing that is not reason enough
还不足以让你重新考虑你的誓言
to make you reconsider your oath,
那你不妨再找一条出路
I suggest you find another.
由诸神之手创造
What was the land immortal hands
从隔离之海中升起的那地是何地
Rose up from Sundering Sea?
恩赐之地 星引之地
-Land of the gift, land of the star
将永远闪耀
To shine eternally?
那是努门诺尔 美丽的努门诺尔
'Twas Númenor Fair Númenor
明亮之岛充满了恩惠优雅…
Bright isle filled with grace...
我就说不会有危险的
I said it won't be dangerous.
我打赌等我下船的时候 一切就都结束了
I wager it'll all be over by the time I get off the boat.
但不要告诉我父亲
Just don't tell my father.
他逢人便夸 未来的女婿是个战争英雄
He keeps crowing to everyone with ears, his future son-in-law's a war hero.
歌唱吧 来吧 唱起来
Sing! Come on, sing.
你还记得歌词吧
You remember the words, don't you?
听你鬼哭狼嚎了一宿 恐怕歌词我永远都忘不掉了
After hearing you squawk them all night, I fear I'll never forget them.
也许伊熙尔杜会和你一起唱
Perhaps Isildur will sing with you.
这就有意思了
This should be interesting.
让我们伟大的岛屿永远屹立 让我们的剑战胜死亡
Make our great land to ever stand Our swords to conquer death
-答案是不行 -我还什么都没说呢
-The answer's no. -I haven't said anything yet.
我认识你15年了
I've known you 15 years.
你真觉得 我不知道你来是要说什么吗
You think I don't know what you're here to say?
-其实是16年 但我的意思是… -安塔摩
-It's actually 16, but I mean... -Ontamo.
好吧 我来是要说什么
Right. What have I come to say?
你要非常诚恳地道歉 当然了 安塔摩肯定会
A fairly lavish apology, which Ontamo, of course,
立马接受道歉 但我可不会
would've accepted instantly, but I wouldn't have.
你知道为什么吗
And do you know why?
你愿意道歉 只是因为你觉得现在我升职了
You're only apologizing because you think now that I've been promoted,
我可以带你参加远征军
I can get you on the expedition.
-可以带我吗  -我就说吧
-Can you? -Right.
我只想说 我不会马上接受你的道歉
I'd just like to say, I wouldn't have accepted instantly.
-我很高兴你道歉了 -他没有
-But I am glad that you apologized. -No, he didn't.
我道歉了
I did!
但我很乐意再道一次 对不起 是我挑起了那次争执
But I'll gladly do it again. I'm sorry I started the fight.
现在请带上我吧
Now please bring me with you.
不行
No.
我到底要怎么做才能弥补过错
What'll it take to make this right?
好吧 你可以随便打我一拳
Fine, you get a free hit.
下巴或肚子都可以 任打一拳
Jaw, gut, your choice. One hit.
三
Three.
二
Uh, two.
其实…
-Actually...
我感觉被打了三拳
That felt like three.
好了 那你们能带我上船吗
So, you'll bring me on the ship?
伊熙尔杜 你是我相处最久的朋友
Isildur, you're my oldest friend.
说实话 现在你可能 仍然是我最好的朋友 但是…
And if you want to know the truth, you're probably still my best, but...
-怎么了  -安塔摩 拜托了
-What? -Ontamo, please.
不行 凭良心 我不能为你背书
I can't, in good conscience, stake my name
推荐你履行一项你可能会放弃的职责
recommending you for a duty that you might well decide to abandon.
这次会不一样的
-It'll be different this time. -Hmm.
我也希望有一天会不一样
One day, I hope it will be.
我也希望有一天你能找到
One day, I hope you find something
愿意为之牺牲一切的东西
that you would be willing to sacrifice anything for.
我会替你照顾贝雷克的 我保证
I'll take care of Berek for you. I promise.
贝雷克要去
Berek's going?
驯马师把他招来了
The horsemaster recruited him.
抱歉 伊熙尔杜 大海永远是正确的
Sorry, Isil. The sea is always right.
你是要偷渡出去吗
Are you stowing away?
你是要把这艘船烧掉吗
Are you about to burn the boat?
马上离开这里 我不会告诉任何人我看到过你
Get out of here this moment. I won't let anyone know I saw you.
-把灯递给我 -别过来
-Hand me the lantern. -Don't.
把灯给我
-Give it.
把大家召集起来 快点
Gather every hand. Hurry!
把他们救上来 快点
Get them out. Quickly.
把他们救上来  伊熙尔杜
Get them out! Isildur?
伊熙尔杜
Isildur?
怎么回事
What happened?
他刚才在一艘渔船上 一定是有酒桶爆炸了
He was in a fishing boat. A cask must've gone up.
酒桶
-A cask?
他救了我的命
He saved my life.
他本可以丢下我 但他却救了我的命
He could've just left, but he saved my life.
船长
Captain!
我们有理由怀疑 是一个经过的强盗所为
We have reason to suspect a passing brigand,
但暂时还没有确认其身份
but we've yet to identify him.
我们很走运 其他的船只没有被烧毁
We're fortunate we didn't lose the rest of the ships as well.
这显然是意图激起你的疑虑 摄政女王
This was clearly an attempt to kindle your doubts, Queen Regent.
-别上当 -我不敢苟同精灵的看法
-Do not let it. -I'm forced to disagree with the Elf.
也许我们确实操之过急了
Perhaps we did act in haste.
王国应该被带领 而不是被拖拽着走
A kingdom should be led. Not dragged.
我建议推迟出航
I recommend we delay the voyage
先为您的事业赢得更多的民心
until we've had time enough to win more hearts to your cause.
敌人一天比一天强大 也许每犹豫一小时 敌人就更强大些
Our enemy grows stronger every day. Perhaps every hour we hesitate.
要记住你为什么 选择了这条路 记住你的信念
Remember why you chose this path. Remember your faith.
你觉得我能忘记吗
Do you think I could forget?
我们还有三艘船 而且还有你父亲的祝福
We still have three ships. And your father's blessing.
哈尔布兰德大人呢
What of Lord Halbrand?
他在等待我们启航
He awaits our departure.
可不是嘛
I'm sure he does.
我要不要让海上卫队先撤下来
Shall I tell the Sea Guard to stand down?
天一亮就重新召开会议 做最后的决定
This council will reconvene at first light to make a final decision.
要确保哈尔布兰德大人参会
See to it Lord Halbrand attends.
你能确定的是什么
What have you been able to ascertain?
埃尔隆德 原谅我
Elrond, forgive me.
原谅你
Forgive you?
原谅我没有早点告诉你
That I did not tell you sooner.
原来你早就知道的
You knew.
从一开始 我就求至高王把我们的秘密告诉你
I begged him to allow you into our confidence from the start,
但他不同意这样做
but the High King forbade it.
这个秘银…
And this... this mithril...
这是我们唯一的救赎吗
It is our only salvation?
埃尔隆德 我在各种恶劣条件下都测试过它
Elrond, I have tested it under every duress.
任何事物都无法削弱它的光
Nothing diminishes its light.
我们相信 如果能快速获得大量秘银
We believe if we can secure vast quantities of it quickly,
多到足以再次 让每一个精灵浸润在维拉之光中…
enough to saturate every last Elf in the light of the Valar once more...
那么 是的
Then, yes.
是的 它是我们唯一的救赎
Yes. It very well could be.
抱歉
I am sorry.
至高王骗了我
That the High King deceived me?
还是说 我们精灵 注定要灭亡 除非我违背誓言
Or that now our people are doomed unless I break an oath?
背叛朋友
And betray a friend?
埃尔隆德 你父亲启航的那个晚上我在场
I was there, Elrond, the night your father set sail.
他一介凡人 相信自己可以说服众神
A mortal man, who believed he could convince the very Gods
让他们参战帮助我们
to come to war in our aid.
我听到你妈妈恳求他不要去
I heard your mother pleading with him not to go,
要求他 哀求他别去 问他为什么非他不可
asking him, imploring him, why, why must it be him?
你知道你父亲说了什么吗
And do you know what he said?
他说因为他是 唯一一个能做这件事的人
Because he was the only one who could do it.
我错了 不应该利用你
I was wrong to use you.
对此 我很抱歉
For that, I'm sorry.
明天 女王会传唤你觐见
Tomorrow, the queen will call you to audience.
你在会面上的态度 很可能会决定这次任务的成败
Your voice at that meeting may well decide whether this mission stands or falls.
-帮帮我 -我想我已经帮你够多了
-Help me. -I think I've helped you quite enough.
那就帮帮你自己
Then help yourself.
别再和我内斗了 跟我一起与敌人战斗
Stop fighting me, and together, let us fight them.
不久前 我这类人却还在与敌人为伍
Not so long ago, men like me were fighting alongside them.
但那是你的同胞 并不包括你
Men like you. Not you, yourself.
你错了
You're wrong.
你不知道 我在坐上那艘木筏之前做了什么
You don't know what I did before I ended up on that raft.
你不知道我是怎么活下来的
You don't know how I survived.
我们所有人是如何得以幸存的
How we all survived.
如果被这些人发现 他们会把我赶出去
And when these people discover it, they will cast me out.
你也一样
So will you.
有时候要找到光 我们必须先触及黑暗
Sometimes to find the light, we must first touch the darkness.
你对黑暗了解多少
What do you know of darkness?
加拉德瑞尔 那把短剑是谁的
Whose dagger was it, Galadriel?
你失去的是谁
Who is it you lost?
我哥哥
My brother.
他出什么事了
What happened to him?
他被杀害了
He was killed.
在一个充斥着黑暗和绝望的地方
In a place of darkness and despair.
被索隆的仆从所杀 这样你满意了吧
By servants of Sauron. Is that enough for you?
所以这是为了复仇
So this is about vengeance?
区区复仇远远无法让我满足
One cannot satisfy thirst by drinking seawater.
那到底是为了什么  你为什么要一直战斗
Then what is it? Why do you keep fighting?
你是在要我去一个 我发誓永远不会回去的地方
You are asking me to go to the one place that I swore never to return.
所以起码你可以告诉我为什么
The least you can do is tell me why.
你为什么要一直战斗
Why do you keep fighting?
因为我停不下来
Because I cannot stop.
我领导的军队对我倒戈相向
The company I led mutinied against me.
我最亲密的朋友 与至高王密谋将我流放
My closest friend conspired with the king to exile me.
我相信他们每个人之所以这样做…
And each of them acted as they did...
是因为他们再也无法将我…
Because I believe they could no longer distinguish me...
与我正在抗争的邪恶区分开来
from the evil I was fighting.
我很遗憾
I'm sorry.
你哥哥的牺牲
For your brother.
以及所有这一切
For all of it.
我替你感到难过
I'm sorry.
你的悲伤无法减轻我的痛苦
Your sorrow cannot ease my pain.
屈尊当个铁匠也不会减轻你的痛苦
And nor will a hammer and tongs ease yours.
你在这里不会找到内心的平静
There is no peace to be found for you here.
我也找不到
And nor for me.
持久的平静在这里无处可寻
No lasting peace in any path,
只能在隔离之海的对岸觅得
but that which lies across the sea.
我已经战斗了几个世纪 试图得到我内心的平静
I have fought for centuries, seeking to earn mine.
你也得这样做才能获得平静
This is how you earn yours.
这一天我已经等待很久了
Long have I awaited this day.
等待您的同类终将归来的这天
The day your kind would return at last,
把我们从淤泥和污秽中拯救出来
lift us up from the muck and the filth,
让我们在您身边找回自己的位置
to take our rightful place at your side.
我向您保证我对您的忠诚至死不渝
I pledge my undying service to you.
我向索隆宣誓效忠
I pledge my loyalty to Sauron.
您是索隆吧
You are Sauron, are you not?
嘿…等等…
Hey, hey... Wait...
那无论您是谁 我都效忠于您
I'll serve you, then. Whoever you are.
只有双手沾血才能证明忠诚
Only blood can bind.
沃德雷格
Waldreg?
沃德雷格…
Waldreg...
沃德雷格 不要
Waldreg, no.
不要…
No.
-No.
不要
No!
下次瞄高一点
Lift your aim next time.
别那么害怕弓弦
And don't be so afraid of the string.
何苦要费心教我
Why bother trying to teach me?
因为我花了两百多年
Because it took me over 200 years
才有了今晚站在这里的勇气
to develop the bravery that's keeping me standing here tonight.
而你仅仅14岁就有这样的勇气了
You found it in only 14.
战斗中我们需要这种勇气
And we're going to need it in the fight to come.
在我一生中 你们精灵一直监视着我们
All my life, your kind has watched us.
清点我们说过的每一句悄悄话
Counting every whisper.
留意每一把过于锋利的餐刀
Every kitchen knife too sharp.
我们都快要被埋在这座瞭望塔里了
We're all about to be buried in this tower.
何苦还要跟我们一起陪葬呢
So why be buried with us?
因为在清点悄悄话和餐刀的时候
Because in counting the whispers and the knives,
我开始了解在它们背后的活生生的人
I've come to know the voices and the hands of those behind them.
我们的人已经走了一半
Half of us just left.
但还有一半选择了留下
But half stayed.
包括你
Including you.
所以 瞄高一点
So lift your aim.
有件事你不知道
There's something you don't know.
我以前见过这个
I've seen this before.
这是一把钥匙
It is a key.
敌人用一些失传的手艺所制 用来奴役你的祖先
Conjured by some forgotten craft of the enemy, to enslave your ancestors.
是什么的钥匙
A key to what?
我不知道
I do not know.
敌方指挥官说过要成为神
The enemy commander spoke of becoming a god.
要在这些土地上给奥克一个家
Of giving the Orcs a home in these lands.
但不管他有什么阴谋 有一点是肯定的
But whatever his design, this much is certain.
敌人知道你儿子 有他需要用来启动计划的东西
Our enemy knows your son has what he needs to enact it.
要多久
How long?
几天吧
Days.
也可能是几个小时
Maybe hours.
我们会活下来的 布隆温
We can survive this, Bronwyn.
有办法
There is a way.
肯定有
There must be.
的确有一个办法
There is one.
不行 向敌人低头 意味着你就夺走了一切
No! Bow to the enemy, and you take away everything.
夺走了子孙后代的一切
From your son, and his sons after him.
你们祖辈辛勤劳作了 整整一个纪元 才赢回了自己的品性
Your people have worked an entire age to earn back their virtue.
仅仅因为一时的绝望 你就要让它前功尽弃吗
Would you undo it all in just one moment of despair?
肯定还有别的办法
There must be another way.
那说出来听听 我求你了
Name it. I beg you.
我没说错吧
See?
你们盯着我们是对的
You were right to watch us.
因为我们注定要堕入黑暗
Because we are destined for the darkness.
这就是我们的生存方式
It's how we survive.
也许我们就是这样的人
Perhaps it's who we are.
永远将会是这样的人
Who we will always be.
处于风险之中的 可远远不只有我们的性命
There's far more at stake here than just our lives.
当年魔苟斯开战 整个贝烈瑞安德都沦陷了
When Morgoth was at war, whole continents sank.
有谁能说得出 这次会引发什么样的可怕后果
Who is to say what horrors this might unleash,
就应该让敌人得逞吗
should our enemy obtain it?
我们有什么力量去阻止他
What power do we have to stop him?
看看周围 已经完蛋了
Look around. It's over.
-还没有 -很快就要完蛋了
-Not yet. -Soon enough.
等敌人向我们进军时 这座瞭望塔就会倒下
And when they march upon us, this tower will fall.
战斗
Nampat!
刚才你是瞎编的 不是吗
You made it up, didn't you?
迪莎多年来 一直想要一张新桌子 所以…
Disa's been wanting a new table for years, so...
快得了 这桌子哪有那么重
Ah, come on, it's not that heavy.
让我感到负担沉重的 不是这张桌子的重量
It is not the weight of the table that burdens me.
那你为什么不说出来
So why don't you come out with it?
因为负担拿出来分担 有可能会减半 也有可能会加倍
Because a burden shared may either be halved or doubled.
取决于听话人的同理心
-Depending on the heart that receives it.
奥力的胡子啊 你别绕弯子了
Aul?'s beard! Enough with the quail sauce.
大大方方说 不用避讳
Give me the meat, and give it to me raw.
我没有对你说实话 都林
I have not been truthful with you, Durin.
我来卡扎督姆 并非为了友谊 而是有目的而来
I did not come to Khazad-d?m for friendship, but ambition.
但我之前并不知情
I did not know it.
我此行的任务是寻找秘银
But I came for mithril.
为什么
Why?
如果没有秘银
Without it,
我们精灵族要么 得在春天离开这些海岸 要么灭亡
my kind must either abandon these shores by spring, or perish.
灭亡
Perish?
怎么灭亡
Perish how?
我们不朽的灵魂将化为乌有
Our immortal souls will dwindle into nothing,
慢慢衰减耗尽
slowly diminishing,
直到我们变成虚影
until we are but shadows,
被时间的潮汐冲走
swept away by the tides of time.
永不复生
Forever.
所以整个精灵族的命运 都掌握在我手中
So the fate of the entire Elven race is in my hands?
看起来是这样的
So it would appear.
再说一次
Say that again.
整个精灵族的命运都掌握在你手中
The fate of the entire Elven race is in your hands.
谁的手中
Whose hands?
你的
Yours.
收起你那软弱的玻璃心 我们走吧
Fetch your feathery shirts. Let's start walking.
-都林… -先别急着谢我
-Durin... -Don't thank me yet.
等我们想办法 说服我父亲之后 再谢我吧
Thank me after we find a way to convince my father.
现在我们可以动身了吗
Now can we please get moving?
回去的路很长
It's a long journey back.
这些阳光都开始让我胃不舒服了
And all this sunlight is startin' to give me a sour stomach.
有个条件 你告诉迪莎这张桌子是我给的
Under one condition. Tell Disa the table's from me.
你别得寸进尺 精灵
Don't push your luck, Elf.
哈尔布兰德大人 摄政女王召见您
Lord Halbrand, the Queen Regent summons you.
看看是谁又靠他爹弄到了一个位置啊
Look whose father secured him a post. Again.
我是自己争取到的 和你一样
I earned mine. Same as you.
士兵
Soldier.
去向驯马师报道
Report to the horsemaster.
我以为我是骑兵
Thought I was in cavalry.
你的确是
You are.
负责清扫马厩
Stable sweep.
士兵们
Soldiers!
解开绳索
Clear the lines!
扬帆远航
Square the sail!
我们朝东北方向行进
We head nor'-east.
前往中洲
For Middle-earth.
耶
Yes!
太阳正在落下
The sun is fast falling
落在森岩的树林后方
Beneath trees of stone
塔中之光
The light in the tower
不再是家乡
No longer my home
过去灯火朦胧
Past eyes of pale fire
黑沙做我的睡床
Black sand for my bed
我用所知的一切
I trade all I've known
换取未知的未来
For the unknown ahead
呼唤我 遥远之地 请呼唤我
Call to me Call to me lands far away
因为我现在 必须在这流浪的日子里游荡
For I must now wander this wandering day
我必须游荡
Away I must wander
在这流浪的日子里
This wandering day
我缺水
Of drink I have little
我少食
And food I have less
我的力量告诉我不行 但是这条路要求我踏足
My strength tells me no But the path demands yes
我双腿很短 而道阻且长
My legs are so short And the way is so long
无法休息 何谈舒适
I've no rest nor comfort
无所慰藉 唯有歌声
No comfort, but song
为我歌唱 遥远之地 请为我歌唱
Sing to me, sing to me Lands far away
请起身指引我度过这流浪的日子
Oh, rise up and guide me This wandering day
请答应要找到我
Please promise to find me
在这流浪的日子里
This wandering day
最终 他们的答案来了
At last comes their answer
穿过寒冷和霜冻
Through cold and through frost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder or wander are lost
不论悲伤
No matter the sorrow
不计成本
No matter the cost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder Or wander are... Lost
字幕翻译：腐哥
创意监督 罗婷婷